A Finding Aid to the Perry Townsend Rathbone papers, 1929-1985, in the Archives of American Art AAA.rathperr
Archives of American Art
Perry Townsend Rathbone papers
1929-1985
AAA.rathperr
Archives of American Art
4.3 Linear feet 5 boxes, 1 OV
The papers of museum director Perry Townsend Rathbone measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1929 to 1985. The papers document Rathbone's career as museum director of the City Art Museum of St. Louis and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and his later work with Christie's New York office. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence with friends and colleagues, writings, professional and project files, printed materials, and photographs, mostly of exhibitions.
Rathbone, Perry Townsend, 1911-2000
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1930-1982 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1940-1985 (1.1 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Writings, 1929-1967 (0.8 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Professional Files, 1938-1984 (2 linear feet; Box 2-4, OV 6)
Series 5: Printed Materials, 1954-1975 (0.2 linear feet; Box 4-5, OV 6)
Series 6: Photographs, 1936-1972 (0.1 linear feet; Box 5)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of museum director Perry Townsend Rathbone measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1929 to 1985. The papers document Rathbone's career as museum director of the City Art Museum of St. Louis and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and his later work with Christie's New York office. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence with friends and colleagues, writings, professional and project files, printed materials, and photographs, mostly of exhibitions.
Biographical materials contain curriculum vitae, biographical sketches, citations for honorary degrees and for Rathbone's appointment as Chevalier of the French Legion of Honor, a passport, a transcript of an interview with Rathbone and articles written by others about Rathbone, including one by S. Lane Faison.
Correspondence is with Rathbone's friends and colleagues. Notable correspondents include Max Beckmann, Xavier Gonzalez, Hanns Swarzenski, Curt Valentin, Jane Sabersky, William R. Valentiner, and Marian Willard, among others. Rathbone knew several art historians and conservators who served in the U.S. Army as members of the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section, also known as the Monuments Men. Correspondence with these colleagues is arranged together as a subseries and includes correspondence with S. Lane Faison, Thomas Carr Howe, Lamont Moore, Charles Parkhurst, Andrew Ritchie, George Leslie Stout, and Otto Wittman. Most of the correspondence with other Monuments Men is post World War II.
Writings by Rathbone consist of student papers, typescript drafts of articles and entries for exhibition catalogs, notes and notebooks from European trips, and lectures.
Professional files encompass a range of documents related to Rathbone's museum directorships, projects, travels and professional affiliations. The folders about his work at the City Art Museum of St. Louis and the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston include correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, press releases and notes. There are also folders on specific projects such as the renovation of the historic Dederer-Blodgett House and Rathbone's membership on various art commissions and committees. Also found within this series are correspondence, notebooks, receipts, itineraries and vouchers for Rathbone's business trips to Europe and other locations while working for the Boston Museum of Fine Arts.
Printed materials include news clippings, articles, press releases, a few art magazines and exhibition catalogues, and invitations to events. There are also black and white photographs of exhibitions, including a Max Beckmann exhibit, and a few images of Rathbone.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Perry Townsend Rathbone donated his paper to the Archives of American Art in 1977 and 1988.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Perry Townsend Rathbone (1911-2000) was a prominent museum director who worked primarily in Boston and New York City. He was an early supporter of German Expressionism in America.
Rathbone was director of the City Art Museum of St. Louis from 1940-1955, moving on to direct the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston from 1954-1972, where he led a period of extensive reform. After retiring from the museum, he worked for one year for the Chase Manhattan Bank as an art consultant. Rathbone worked as director and senior vice president of Christies USA auction house from 1973-1987. After 1987, he continued working at Christies as a consultant.
Rathbone was born in Germantown, Pennsylvania on July 3, 1911 and grew up in New Rochelle, New York. He attended Harvard College, majoring in Art History and graduating in 1933. He then completed the graduate "museum course" taught by Professor Paul Sachs in 1934. The Paul Sachs museum course was famous for cultivating future directors at some of this country's most prestigious museums. After Harvard, Rathbone was appointed as curator of Alger House (later renamed the Grosse Pointe War Memorial), a branch of the Detroit Institute of Arts. Rathbone directed the ''Masterpieces of Art'' exhibit at the 1939 New York World's Fair. The success of the exhibit led to his appointment as director of the City Art Museum of St. Louis, Missouri in 1940 at the age of 29, making him the youngest American museum director at the time.
During World War II, Rathbone served in the U.S. Navy from late 1942-1945. He was a commissioned officer in charge of the Navy Art and Poster Section, Office of Public Relations in Washington, D.C. He supervised five Navy "combat artists," who painted naval battles and depicted the daily lives of soldiers. He also served as an officer in New Calcedonia. He separated from service as a Lieutenant Commander in late 1945. This collection does not contain records directly related to his military service. In 1945 Rathbone married Euretta de Cosson while on leave in Washington, D.C. They had three children together: Peter, Eliza, and Belinda.
Rathbone resumed his position as the director of the City Art Museum of St. Louis after the war. The Detroit Institute of Arts director William R. Valentiner introduced Rathbone to German Expressionism. Rathbone helped the German Expressionist painter Max Beckmann, labeled a ''degenerate artist'' by Hitler, and his wife immigrate to America and then arranged a teaching position for Beckmann at Washington University. Rathbone and Beckmann became close, and in 1948, Rathbone organized a Beckmann retrospective at the City Art Museum. Beckmann made a portrait of Rathbone and one of his wife Euretta. Rathbone gave the eulogy at Beckmann's funeral in 1950.
In 1955 Rathbone became the director of the Museum of Fine Arts (MFA) in Boston. During his tenure there he expanded the museum by 80,000 square feet, doubled the staff, and oversaw the renovations of 57 of the Museum's 189 galleries. He mounted exhibitions of Rembrandt, Matisse, Modigliani, Cezanne, van Gogh and Courbet. The Boston Museum's first acquisitions of Pablo Picasso, Alexander Calder, Constantine Brancusi, Paul Klee, Alberto Giacometti and other works by 20th-century artists occurred under Rathbone's directorship. Rathbone also served as curator of paintings and wrote the catalog essays for many of the museum's exhibitions. Working with Frances Weeks Hallowell, he established the first "Ladies Committee" for the museum, which substantially increased membership. He was appointed as Chevalier de Légion d'Honneur by the French government in 1964.
In 1969, the Museum of Fine Arts purchased what was believed to be a Raphael portrait of Eleonora Gonzaga, 1505, from a Genoa art dealer. The work was meant to be the highlight of the museum's centennial celebration. However controversy arose when the Italian government alleged that the work was smuggled out of the country and the museum was forced to return the painting to the Italian government. The situation caused Rathbone to resign in 1972.
At the request of David Rockefeller, Rathbone became an art consultant to Chase Manhattan Bank for one year. In 1973, he became director of Christie's auction house in New York and senior vice president in 1977, working there until 1987, when he retired but still worked as a consultant.
Perry Townsend Rathbone died on January 22, 2000 at the age of 88.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds an oral history interview of Perry Townsend Rathbone conducted in 1975-1976 by Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art's oral history program.
Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section.; Beckmann, Max, 1884-1950; Christie, Manson & Woods International Inc..; City Art Museum of St. Louis; Faison, S. Lane (Samson Lane), 1907-2006; Gonzalez, Xavier, 1898-1993; Howe, Thomas Carr, 1904-1994; Moore, Lamont; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.; Parkhurst, Charles; Ritchie, Andrew Carnduff; Sabersky, Jane, 1911-1983; Stout, George L. (George Leslie); Swarzenski, Hanns, 1903-1985; Valentin, Curt, 1902-1954; Valentiner, Wilhelm Reinhold, 1880-1958; Willard, Marian, 1904-; Wittmann, Otto, 1911-2001; Interviews; Museum directors--Massachusetts--Boston; Photographs; Transcripts
- Biographical Materials, 1930-1982; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains Rathbone's curriculum vitaes; a Harvard textbook; biographical and autobiographical sketches; citations for honorary degrees from various universities and for his appointment as Chevalier of the French Legion of Honor; a passport and passport photographs; a transcript of an interview with Rathbone; articles about his professional achievements; and an obituary for his mother Beatrice Connely Rathbone.
  Arrangement note
  The documents are arranged chronologically with the curriculum vitae grouped together at the start of the series.
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harvard Fine Arts 1d Textbook, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Commemorative Poems, circa 1956; circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Short Bio for Harvard's 25th Annual Report, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Northeastern University Honorary Degree, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beatrice Connely Rathbone Obituary, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Beatrice Connely Rathbone was Perry T. Rathbone's mother.
  - Passport Photos, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passport, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Who's Who in America Biographical Sketch, 1962; 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chevalier of the Legion of Honor Citation, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "How to Become an Art Collector" by Leona Rubin, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Article about Perry T. Rathbone.
  - Transcript of Interview with Perry Rathbone, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Short Bio for Harvard 35th Anniversary Report, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Suffolk University Honorary Degree, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "MFA Boston: The Rathbone Years" by S. Lane Faison, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Cyclopedia of American Biography Profile, circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Professional Profile for WBOS Radio, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1940-1985; Series 2; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Correspondence is with friends, colleagues, and members of U.S. Army's Monuments, Fine Arts & Archives Section who went on to successful careers in the arts after World War II. The bulk of the correspondence is related to Rathbone's work as a museum director and dates from after the war. Correspondents include the German Expressionist painter Max Beckmann, Detroit Institute of the Arts director William R. Valentiner, Harvard professor Paul Sachs, Boston Museum of Fine Arts curator Hanns Swarzenski, and many others. A letter from Beatrice Connely Rathbone, Rathbone's mother, is the only family correspondence. Also found here are scattered letters from fellow art historians who served as Monuments Men during World War II, although the bulk of the letters post date the war.
  Correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order according to surname. Correspondents with fewer than three letters are grouped in general alphabetical folders at the end of the subseries. The last folder of unidentified correspondence contains letters from individuals whose names were illegible or their surnames were not included in the text.
  - Attwill, J. Sanger, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bachrach, Bradford, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bartholet, E. Ives, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Beckmann, Max and Quappi, 1947-1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bickford, Nathaniel J., 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Boggis, B. S., 1954; 1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Carre, Louis, 1972-1973; 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cavallo, Adolph S., 1954; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Coates, Thomas, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cogswell, Margaret, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Congdon, William, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Coolidge, John, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Coremans, Paul, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cox, Jan, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Crawford, (Lord), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cummings, Willard W., 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cunningham, Charles C., 1954; 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Deely, James Sedgwick, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - DeNormandie, Alice, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dmitri, Ivan, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Douglas, R. Langton, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Eastman, John, Jr., 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Eaton, Violet, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Ede, H. S., 1951-1954; 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Eisendrath, Willliam N., Jr., 1954-1955; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Evans, Arthur R., Jr., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Faison, S. Lane, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Fenton, John E., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Fourcade, Xavier, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Goepel, Erhard, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Griswold, James W., 1973; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hallstein, Walter, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Harriman, Marie N., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Harris, Paul S., 1954-1955; 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Hatch, Francis W., 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Hayes, Bartlett H., 1946-1954; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Hofer, Phil, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Hood, Gilbert H., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Howe, Thomas Carr, 1954-1957; 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Hurwitz, Sidney, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Jerichow, John H., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Katz, Ralph, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Kefauver, Nancy P., 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Kelleher, Patrick J., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Kennedy, Edward M., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Kligerman, Joshua, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Kokoschka, Oskar, 1954; 1946 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Ladd, S. Parker, II, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Lenart, Gertrude, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Leylan, Robert M., 1954-1955; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Lipman, Jean, 1946; 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Loevenich, Karl, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Low, Frank H., 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Luckey, Laura, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Marini, Marino, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - McAndrew, John, 1970; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - McCrae, Stephen R., 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - McIlhenny, Henry P., 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Mittwer, Henry, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Moore, Fanny H., 1955; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Moore, Henry, 1971-1975; 1954 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Moore, Lamont, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Muller, Rene, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Nagel, Charles, 1972; circa 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Osgood, William B., 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Parkhurst, Charles P., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Peabody, James, 1975; 1973 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Phillips, Charles F., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Plaut, James S., 1940-1957; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Pope, John and Annemarie, 1954; 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Price, Lucien, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Proctor, Dorothy, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Rathbone, Beatrice Connely, circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Read, Helen Appleton, 1972; 1954 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Redmond, Roland L., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Ritchie, Andrew, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Robinson, Frederick B., 1940-1972 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Roth, Frank, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Ross, Marvin C., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Sabersky, Jane, circa 1942-1954; 1971 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Sachs, Paul J., 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Sayre, Eleanor, 1973-977 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Schaeffer, H. S., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Schmidt, A. W., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Schmidt, Robert, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Schroeder, Margaretta Oliver, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Seldis, Henry J., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Sere, Claude, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Seybolt, George C., 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Sickman, Laurence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Sizer, Theodore, circa 1940; 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Speyer, Gerard W., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Stoll, Germaine, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Stout, George Leslie, 1954-1971 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Swarzenski, Hanns, 1971-1985; 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Taylor, Francis Henry, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Trovato, Joseph S., 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Thiry, Gertrude, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Valentin, Curt, circa 1940-1954 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Valentiner, William R., circa 1940-1942; 1954 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Vermeule, Cornelius C., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - de Vries, A. B., 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Whitehill, Walter Muir, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Willard, Marian, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Wittman, Otto, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Wragg, Thomas S., 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Yamaguchi, Seiichi, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Yamanaka, Shoji, 1973; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - A-B, 1940-1977 (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - C-D, 1940-1978 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - E-G, 1954-1982 (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - H-K, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - L-M, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - N-P, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - R-S, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - T-Z, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The letter sent by Mike (last name unknown) on September 1, 1980 includes color photographs of Perry T. Rathbone.
- Writings, 1929-1967; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2
  Writings include Rathbone's student papers from Harvard, both his college courses and graduate "museum course" taught by Paul Sachs; typescript drafts of essays he wrote for exhibition catalogues, magazines, journals and memorial services; and lectures for various events at universities, symposiums, etc.
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  3.1: Student Papers, 1929-1934
  3.2: Typescript Drafts, 1940-1967
  3.3: Lectures, circa 1937-circa 1963
  - Student Papers, 1929-1934; 3.1
    - Fine Arts 15b: Exercises in Methods and Progress Papers, 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Book Reviews, 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "A Winslow Homer at the Fogg", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Reports on the Worcester Museum, The Rhode Island School of Design, and Fenway Court", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The First Masterpiece of Augustus Saint-Gaudens: A ten minute radio talk", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "The Problem of Juan de Burgos", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Two Panels from the High Altarpiece of Santa Maria del Mar, Barcelona", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The Greek Revival in America", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Analysis of a Thesis for Professor Post", 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "The History of French Furniture in the 18th Century", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "The Iconography of Several Paintings in the Fogg Museum and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts", 1932 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "The Style of Carlo Crivelli", 1932 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "The Romanesque Facade in Tuscany", 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "A Catalan Triptych at Fenway Court", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Madonna of Mercy from the Cathedral of Teruel", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Siena, Italy", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "The So-Called Portrait of Ascencio Julia in the Fogg Museum", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Typescript Drafts, 1940-1967; 3.2
    Arranged here are mostly typescript drafts of articles and essays for magazines, journals, newspapers, exhibition catalogues, museum bulletins, and a few memorial speeches for friends and colleagues. Many drafts include edits and marginalia. A few folders hold multiple drafts of an article.
    - "Landmarks in Modern German Art Expression", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "The Housekeeper by Nicholas Maes", circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Writings from the City Art Museum, St. Louis, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Writings from the City Art Museum, St. Louis, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Writings from the City Art Museum, St. Louis, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "The Art of the Mississippi", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Taste in St. Louis," St. Louis Dispatch 75th Anniversary, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Article for The Christian Science Monitor, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous Forewords, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "George Catlin," Art in America, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Article for Arts of Virginia Spring Issue, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Articles for Boston Museum of Fine Arts Bulletins, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Article about Adelyn Breeskin in the Baltimore Museum News Quarterly, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "The Stylistic Development and Symbolism of Max Beckmann", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Copley's Corkscrew," Art in America, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Max Beckmann Biography for the Encyclopedia Americana, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Memo for Sunday Advertiser, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Obituary for Robert Treat Paine, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "Paul J. Sachs as Teacher," St. Louis Post Dispatch, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Photography in the Fine Arts", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Museums in the Boston Area", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Introduction for the 1968 Scientific Seminar Catalogue, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Article for Boston Institute of Contemporary Art "5 Museum Directors' Selections" Exhibit, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Henry Preston Rossiter, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Andrew Wyeth, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Introduction to Painting Catalogue, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Henry Rossiter Memorial, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - George Leslie Stout Memorial, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Max Beckmann Memorial, circa 1955 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      Handwritten draft
    - Rogier van der Wyden, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Handwritten notes.
  - Lectures, circa 1937-circa 1963; 3.3
    The lectures in this subseries span the course of Rathbone's career from the Detroit Institute of the Arts and the St. Louis City Art Museum to the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. The lectures are mostly about exhibitions in addition to a few about Max Beckmann. There is one lecture by Max Beckmann at the end of the subseries.
    - "The Spirit of the Renaissance" at the Detroit Institute of the Arts, circa 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - "The City Art Museum of St. Louis", 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Installation of the City Art Museum Period Rooms, 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Untitled Lecture about "matching art and music", circa 1945-circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 57)